## **Biographical Sketch**

Dr. Lois Wright Morton Professor of Sociology

Interim Director of the Leopold Center for Sustainable Agriculture
Department of Sociology 317C East Hall Office Tel: (515) 294-2843
Iowa State University Home Tel: (641) 377-3100

Ames, Iowa 50011-1070 Fax: (515) 294-0592

#### Education

Cornell University, New York Development Sociology	PhD	1998
Syracuse University, New York College for Human Development	MS	1977
Bowling Green State University, Ohio Home Economics Education	n BS	1972

## **Professional Experience**

Interim Director of the Leopold Center for Sustainable Agriculture (2010- current) Professor (2010-current) Dept of Sociology, Iowa State University, Ames, IA Associate Professor (2005-2010) Dept of Sociology, Iowa State University, Ames, IA. Assistant Professor (1999-2005) Dept of Sociology, Iowa State University, Ames, IA. Senior Extension Associate (1993-1999) Dept of Policy Analysis and Management, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY.

Self-employed farmer (1986-1992)

Instructor (1981-1985) Syracuse University, University College and College for Human Development, Syracuse, NY.

Cooperative Extension Agent (1973-1979) Cornell Cooperative Extension, Syracuse, NY.

### **Selected Journal Articles**

Morton, L.W., E. Regen, D. M. Engle, and J. R. Miller. (in press) "Perceptions of Landowners Concerning Conservation, Grazing, Fire, and Eastern Redcedar Management in Tallgrass Prairie." *Rangeland Ecology & Management*.

Morton, L. W. and Chih Yuan Weng. 2009. "Getting to Better Water Quality Outcomes: The Promise & Challenge of the Citizen Effect." *Agriculture and Human Values*. 26 (1): 83-94.

Smith, C. and L. W. Morton. 2009. "Rural Food Deserts: Low Income Perspectives on Food Access in Minnesota and Iowa." *Journal of Nutrition Education and Behavior* 41(May-June):176-187.

Morton, L. W. and C. Smith. 2008. "Accessing Food in Rural Food Deserts in Iowa and Minnesota." *Great Plains Sociologist* 19:57-82.

Morton, L. W., Y. C. Chen, and R. Morse. 2008. "Small Town Civic Structure and Intergovernment Collaboration for Public Services." *City & Community* 7(1): 45-60.

Morton, L. W. 2008. "The Role of Civic Structure in Achieving Performance-based Watershed Management." *Society & Natural Resources* 21(9):751-766.

Morton, L.W., A. Bitto, M.J. Oakland, M. Sand. 2008. "Accessing Food Resources: Rural and Urban Patterns of Giving and Getting Food" *Agriculture and Human Values* 25:107-119.

Morton, L.W. and L. W. Miller. 2007. "Connecting Sustainable Agriculture to Rural Development: The Case of Pasture-Based Dairy Grazing" *Journal of Community Development* 38:3:23-38.

Allen, B. and L.W. Morton. 2006. "Shared Leadership Practices Among Non-Profits in Iowa" *Journal of Extension*. December 44:6:1-12 <a href="https://www.joe.org">www.joe.org</a>

Morton, L. W. and S. Padgitt. 2005. "Selecting Socio-Economic Metrics for Watershed Management." *Environmental Monitoring & Assessment*. 103:83-98.

### **Selected Books**

Morton, L.W and S.S. Brown (eds) (In press) *Pathways for Getting to Better Water Quality: The Citizen Effect*. Springer Science + Business.

### **Selected Extension Publications**

Wortmann, C. S., M. Helmers, B. Gelder, L. W. Morton, D. Devlin, C. Barden, S. Anderson, R. Broz, T. Franti, T. Regassa, P. Shea, M. Tomer, L. Frees, and D. Griffith. 2008. *Targeting of Watershed Management: Practices for Water Quality Protection* Heartland Regional Water Coordination Initiative, University of Nebraska Lincoln.

Morton, L.W., Brown, S. (2007). Water Issues in the Four State Heartland Region: A Survey of Public Perceptions and Attitudes about Water The Heartland Regional Water Coordination Initiative Bulletin #SP289 Iowa State University Extension <a href="http://www.heartlandwq.iastate.edu">http://www.heartlandwq.iastate.edu</a>

Morton, L.W., J. Rodecap, S. Brown, G.A. Miller. 2006. *Performance-based Environmental Management: The Hewitt Creek Model.* Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa. University Extension Bulletin PM 2013

# Synergistic Activities

\*Project director for the Heartland Integrated Water Quality Coordination project, a partnership of Iowa State University, Kansas State University, the University of Missouri, and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the USDA NIFA National Integrated Water Quality Program and US EPA Region 7. Also team leader of the Human Dimensions group working across water quality themes to integrate human and social aspects into watershed management, bioenergy and water resources, and nutrient management. The project goal is to build institutional partnerships and increase the capacity of citizens, educators, agencies and community leaders to better address water quality concerns.

- \* Lead PI of a USDA grant to develop local leadership & extension capacity for performance based agricultural management. The project consists of a team of faculty and staff representing Agronomy, Agriculture and Biosystems Engineering, Sociology and Extension field specialists responsible for the organization of locally-managed watershed projects and the development of statewide capacity for watershed support. \* Team scientist of the Working Landscape Research Team, a 3-state, multi-disciplinary team of landscape ecologists, entomologists, sociologist, and avian experts with research on grassland/prairie restoration that involves transfer of scientific knowledge on public reserves to private landowners.
- \*Interim Director of the Leopold Center for Sustainable Agriculture. The Center, through a competitive grants program, incentivizes research, extension/outreach, and producer innovative practices that promote profitable agricultural livelihoods and healthy, sustainable and resilient ecosystems. Programming foci are food systems, ecology, public policy and the Iowa Learning Farm (a partnership of state agencies and voluntary organizations with natural resource protection missions).